Today's דף Daf is סמך, Samach, 60. We start at the very
bottom of נט עמוד ב Nun Tet Amud Bet in the משנה.
Mishnah. And the first משנה Mishnah was about basically the schedule of
the day and when normally the afternoon תמיד Tamid would be brought
and when it would be brought on ערב פסח Erev Pesach to
give time for the bringing of the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach and
although the general rule is you don't bring any קרבנות korbanot after
the afternoon תמיד, Tamid, the פסח Pesach was the exception to that
rule and it was brought later in the afternoon but you still
wanted to give plenty of time for everybody to bring their קרבן
פסח. Korban Pesach. The משנה Mishnah now turns to not the question
of the actual bringing of the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach and starts
with the issue of how it was shechted.
And in this way it's somewhat similar to the very opening משנה
Mishnah of זבחים Zevachim as I was mentioned that now we're go
in sections that easily could be in סדר קדשים Seder Kodashim this
whole next few פרקים prakim and the beginning of that of זבחים
Zevachim opens up with the question about if you shecht a קרבן
שלא לשמו, korban shelo lishmo, not for its intended purpose. Either with
the intention of a different owner or the simpler case is with
the intention of you thinking you you think that it's a different
קרבן korban than it actually is. And I should mention that the
general rule in that משנה Mishnah is כל הזבחים ששחטן שלא לשמן
כשרים אלא שלא עלו לבעלים לשם חובה Kol hazvachim sheshchtan shelo lishmon
ksheirin ela shelo alu labaalim lesheim hovah that any קרבן korban that
you shecht for a different purpose: you're bringing a שלמים shelamim and
in my head I think it's an עולה, olah, or you're bringing
an עולה olah and in my head I think it's a חטאת
chatat or whatever it is, it's still כשר. kasher. You can bring
the קרבן, korban, you can sprinkle the blood or throw the blood,
you can eat the meat, you can burn the fats. But if
I had, I the כהן, kohen, had the intention of the wrong
type of קרבן, korban, then you do not fulfill your obligation. The
קרבן korban as an object is a legitimate קרבן korban but in
terms of you and you having bringing this to satisfy whatever obligation
you have, it doesn't count for you. And then that's even more
severe in the case of the חטאת chatat or the sin offering.
The sin offering because the whole point of the חטאת chatat is
to come to atone for your sin. It's all about it being
your קרבן. korban. You don't have a חטאת chatat that's brought without
a specific relationship to the owner and the sin. So therefore also
חטאת chatat can be for purification but specifically is about the owner.
So once I do it שלא לשמו shelo lishmo and that has
the effect of detaching it from being yours, then it then it
actually is completely invalid. So the חטאת שלא לשמו chatat shelo lishmo
is invalid. In our משנה, Mishnah, we're going to see that that
same rule applies to the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. פסח Pesach although
it's a lighter קרבן, korban, it's a שלמים, shelamim, the owners eat
from it and so on, it has this weighty rule that שלא
לשמו shelo lishmo makes it completely invalid. Let's take a look at
this first משנה. Mishnah.
Is that the same as פיגול? pigul?
פיגול pigul no. פיגול pigul is when you intend to eat it
at the wrong time or variation of that which isn't technically פיגול
pigul in the wrong place. Okay that also invalidates, but that's not
this. This is just you thinking in your head that it's a
חטאת chatat when it's a שלמים shelamim or you think it's an
עולה olah when it's a חטאת chatat or something like that.
פיגול pigul is also the צד השוה tzad hashaveh פיגול pigul though
is also it's dependent upon one's intent.
Right. The כהן's kohen thoughts. And I should mention another important point
that also comes up at the very beginning of זבחים Zevachim that
first of all we're talking about the כהן, kohen, not the owner.
Whether the owner's thoughts have any relevance we can discuss, but primarily
we're talking about the כהן. kohen. And number two is is that
there is a general position in רש״י Rashi and תוספות, Tosafot, whatever,
that when talking about thought, we actually mean articulated thought, that it
has to be verbalized
and there's a whole question if the כהן kohen says I was
thinking this but he never actually said that out loud whether that
has any effect whatsoever. Let's just read the משנה Mishnah and then
I'll take the question. I first want to just ground us in
the first in this משנה. Mishnah. הפסח ששחטן שלא לשמו: Hapesach sheshchtan
shelo lishmo: if you shecht the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach שלא לשמו
shelo lishmo for for purpose of a different קרבן. korban. We'll talk
about the wrong owners in the next משנה, Mishnah, but here the
purpose is for a different קרבן. korban. וקיבל והילך וזרק שלא לשמו:
Vekibel vehilach vezarak shelo lishmo: this ו vav obviously means 'or'. Or
you caught the blood. There are four primary עבודות avodot with the
blood that and in each one of those from the time of
the שחיטה shechitah till the blood gets put on the altar and
each one of those if you have the wrong thought at that
time you can invalidate the קרבן. korban. What are those four עבודות?
avodot? They are the slaughtering, then the catching of the blood. The
blood squirts out of the animal's neck and there's some כהן kohen
there with a basin and with some type of of a dish
which he catches the blood in. והילך: Vehilach: then he would he
walk that blood to the altar. וזרק: vezarak: and you throw the
blood on the altar. Those are the four עבודות: avodot: שחיטה, shechitah,
קבלה, kabbalah, הולכה, holachah, וזריקה. vezrika. If in any one of those
times you had the intention שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, thinking it was
a different קרבן, korban, או לשמו ושלא לשמו, o lishmo veshelo lishmo,
or you had some mixed intention, and this is going to be
what the גמרא's Gemara going to focus on. You thought it was
a פסח Pesach and then maybe a minute later you thought it
was a שלמים shelamim or a חטאת chatat
or
או o or
variation of פסול pasul anytime anything whether it's any one of those
four עבודות avodot and whether it's a complete intention or a mixed
intention, if part of the intention is for the wrong קרבן, korban,
it is invalid. Okay, just like a חטאת, chatas, these are the
two קרבנות korbanot where the intention of the wrong
קרבן korban invalidates. כיצד לשמה ושלא לשמה? Keitzad lishmah u'shelo lishmah? What
is the example of
לשמה ושלא לשמה? lishmah u'shelo lishmah? לשם פסח ולשם שלמים, Leshem Pesach
u'leshem shelamim, you slaughtered and you think it's a פסח Pesach and
you think it's a שלמים shelamim a minute later. שלא לשמה ולשמה?
Shelo lishmah u'lishmah? How about if it's, what's the reverse case? The
wrong intention and the right one, לשם שלמים ולשם פסח. leshem shelamim
u'leshem Pesach. Okay. So anyway, that obviously needs more to be said
here about when did you have these two intentions? At the same
time, at sequential times? That will be discussed in the גמרא, Gemara,
but the general rule is any one of four עבודות, avodot, the
intention of שלא לשמה shelo lishmah is relevant and the פסח Pesach
is more strict like it is like a חטאת chatas that the
שלא לשמה shelo lishmah invalidates, and even if it's a mixed intention
and not a pure שלא לשמה, shelo lishmah, that is enough to
invalidate. Yes, Charlie, you have a question?
Yeah, and non-priest can do the שחיטה? shechitah?
That is correct. Thank you. A non-כהן kohen can do the שחיטה.
shechitah. We normally assume it's the כהנים, kohanim, but still the point
is that it's the emphasis here's on the person doing the עבודה,
avodah, not on the owner of the קרבן. korban. You are correct
that a non-כהן kohen could do the שחיטה. shechitah. Okay, so let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Okay,
בעי רב פפא. Ba'ei Rav Pappa. רב פפא Rav Pappa asks. I
do want to just say one thing about why שלא לשמה shelo
lishmah might be more strict by פסח Pesach and we are going
to find out very soon that קרבן פסח korban Pesach is a
fascinating קרבן korban in that all קרבנות, korbanot, the primary purpose of
the קרבן korban is what? When I bring a קרבן? korban? Like,
you know, wouldn't say atonement, it's not always about a חטאת, chatas,
but what sort of is the focal moment of the קרבן korban
when I bring it? What would you say of all of the
things that it does? שחיטה, shechitah, קבלה, kabalah, זריקה? zrikah? The זריקת
הדם, zrikat hadam, right? Although maybe in our mind we think about
the burning and the smoke going up, but the תורה Torah and
הלכה halachah certainly emphasizes the זריקת הדם. zrikat hadam. It's all about
that.
And however, by a קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, what is the focal
moment? Eating? The eating of it. And the קרבן פסח korban Pesach
is the one קרבן korban that is brought primarily for the purpose
of the eating. The eating is not just one of the things
you do with it after, right? By a קרבן korban you have
to eat, the כהנים, kohanim, the owners, some get burned, right? But
the eating is like a secondary consideration to the bringing. By the
קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, it is all brought לשם אכילה, leshem achilah,
and that is going to be relevant in a number of interesting
הלכות halachot as we will see that makes the קרבן פסח korban
Pesach unique. So, now we also know that the idea of eating
is איש לפי אכלו תכסו על השה, ish lefi ochlo tachosu al
haseh, that you slaughter it, you count, you know, it's a, you
know, it's קחו לכם איש שה לבית אבות, kechu lachem ish seh
lveit avot, you get to get a group that is associated with
the קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. And that is the only group that
is entitled to eat from it. So to eat from it requires
it be the קרבן korban of this group and not of another
group. So it might be that that's linked to why שלא לשמה
shelo lishmah invalidates by פסח. Pesach. The same way by חטאת, chatas,
what שלא לשמה shelo lishmah has the effect by all קרבנות korbanot
doing is it severs the relationship with the owner. Now by most
קרבנות korbanot fine, you have a שלמים shelamim that doesn't have an
owner, you have an עולה olah that doesn't have an owner, you
still bring it. But a חטאת, chatas, you can't have a חטאת
chatas without an owner. A חטאת chatas is about the owner's sin,
and therefore without an owner, it becomes invalid. Well, a פסח Pesach
as well, it's all about its being eaten, and the eating only
is in connection with the designated owners of the קרבן, korban, and
as soon as that relationship is broken, is severed, there's no longer
any purpose to a פסח Pesach without owners, which is essentially a
פסח Pesach without people that can eat it. So therefore, that might
be why the פסח Pesach like the חטאת chatas שלא לשמה shelo
lishmah invalidates, but we will see more of this, but it is
worth keeping in mind the unique aspect of פסח Pesach is all
about eating, and the eating as opposed to anything else, right? Any
other קרבן, korban, if it's a חטאת, chatas, who eats it? Whoever
the male כהנים kohanim are at that time. If it's a שלמים,
shelamim, whoever eats it? Whoever the owner wants to share it with.
But a פסח, Pesach, the eating is specifically about the group that
was designated when it was being brought.
Yes. The קרבן תודה korban todah would seem to be a little
bit intermediate because it's a... it's like a שלמים shelamim but it's
connected to a specific person required to give thanks.
That is true, but it's חז"ל Chazal more that sort of creates
that sense of obligation and satisfying the obligation. In the תורה, Torah,
it just speaks about a person choosing to bring the תודה, todah,
but that's an interesting point. Okay, look, it's not always completely true,
an אשם asham is also for sin and for atonement, and although
there's a
debate... Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. בעי
רב פפא *Ba’ei Rav Pappa*, so רב פפא *Rav Pappa* asked, בעבודה
אחת b'avoda achas, תנן
או בשתי עבודות avodot. תנן *b’avodah achas tnan o bishtei avodos tnan*?
When it says you have these two thoughts, לשמה lishma *lishma* and
שלא לשמה shelo lishma *shelo lishma*, are they all during one עבודה
avoda *avodah*? The עבודה avoda, *avodah* is these four acts: שחיטה shechita
*shachting*, שחיטה shechita, *shechitah*, קבלה *kabbalah*, הולכה *holachah*, and זריקת הדם *zrikas
hadam*.
So is it two thoughts during one act or are they two
separate acts? So now he's going to explain, בעבודה אחת תנן רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose. היא *b’avodah achas tnan Rabbi Yose hi*, דאמר אף
בגמר דבריו אדם נתפס *damar af bigmar devarav adam nitpas*. A person
is grabbed, is held accountable as it were, even for the end
of his words. ואי רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *ve-ei Rabbi Meir*, הא
אמר תפוס לשון ראשון *ha amar tfos lashon rishon*. He says you
go by the beginning of the words. This is a כלל *klal*
case, we dealt with this earlier in the מסכת *maseches*. If a
person says הרי זה תמורת עולה תמורת שלמים Shelamim *harei ze tmuras
olah tmuras shelamim*, he says a statement which is contradictory. This קרבן
korban *korban* is substitute for an עולה *olah*, substitute for a שלמים
Shelamim? *shelamim*. You can't have something that is both; it's one or
the other. So how do you interpret a sentence that's a hybrid
statement that the whole sentence can't be true under normal, you know,
normal rules? So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says you only
look at the beginning. The first part made sense, הרי זה תמורת
עולה *harei ze tmuras olah*, you ignore the end. Okay, so you
ignore the end statement. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose. *Rabbi Yose* says, no,
you look at the whole sentence, beginning and the end, and if
he created some hybrid even though normally it doesn't exist, we have
to find some way to give halachic meaning to this hybrid, this
is what he tried to create. So רבי יוסי'ס *Rabbi Yose's* position
is אף בגמר דבריו אדם נתפס *af bigmar devarav adam nitpas*. Even
if the end of your sentence somehow creates a contradiction with the
beginning of it, you're held accountable to all of it. רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says you just look at the beginning. So
if it's one עבודה avoda *avodah* and I am שחיטה shechita. *shachting*
and I'm saying I am שחיטה shechita, *shachting* this for the sake
of a פסח Pesach, *pesach*, for the sake of a שלמים shelamim
*shelamim*, doesn't make sense. What is it, פסח Pesach *pesach* or שלמים
shelamim. *shelamim*? So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* would say fine,
you pick, you know, ignore the end of the sentence. It doesn't
make sense if you add the end. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose. *Rabbi
Yose* says I'm sorry, you look at the whole sentence, and I
don't know what he means but he says both, and since he
said both, both, part of it is שלא לשמה shelo lishma, *shelo
lishma* and it's invalid. So if we're talking about these hybrid thoughts
during one עבודה avoda *avodah*, it only works according to רבי יוסי
*Rabbi Yose* who says you look at the entire statement, אף בגמר
דבריו אדם נתפס *af bigmar devarav adam nitpas*. ואי רבי מאיר *ve-ei
Rabbi Meir*, to repeat it again, if it were רבי מאיר *Rabbi
Meir*, הא אמר תפוס לשון ראשון *ha amar tfos lashon rishon*, he
would just put the period after the first phrase and the second
thing you said would not be relevant, it's all one sentence. So
is that משנה Mishnah *mishnah*? Then it's according to רבי יוסי *Rabbi
Yose*. או דלמא *o dilma*, top of סמך *samech*, or do you
say בשתי עבודות avodot תנן *bishtei avodos tnan*? We're talking about two
separate עבודות avodot *avodos*. When you're שחיטה shechita, *shachting* it you're saying
לשם פסח Pesach *l'shem pesach* and when you're catching the blood or
throwing the blood you're saying לשם שלמים leshem shelamim. *l'shem shelamim*. ואפילו
רבי מאיר דאמר תפוס לשון ראשון *va-afilu Rabbi Meir damar tfos lashon
rishon*, and even רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* says you go by the
first part of the sentence, הני מילי בעבודה אחת *hani mili b'avodah
achas*, that's when it's during one עבודה avoda *avodah*, essentially one contradictory
sentence, so he only looks at the first half. אבל בשתי עבודות
avodos. מודה *aval bishtei avodos modeh*, but if two acts he would
agree דמיפסל *de-mifsil* that it becomes invalid because when you said פסח
Pesach, *pesach* that was a good עבודה avoda. *avodah* and the next
עבודה avoda. *avodah* when you said שלמים shelamim, *shelamim* that was invalid.
Okay, so certainly you could have separate sentences which we would, each
one would carry its own weight, and therefore even רבי מאיר *Rabbi
Meir* would agree if it was during two עבודות avodos *avodos*. The
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has no question what the הלכה Halacha *halachah* is.
If it's two עבודות avodos *avodos*, everybody agrees it's no good. If
it's one עבודה avoda *avodah*, it's the debate of רבי מאיר *Rabbi
Meir*, רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose*. Our question is which scenario our משנה
Mishnah. *mishnah* was referring to. So then the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* first
also qualifies its question. אמרי אהיי *amri ahay*. Now you could say
on which one are you talking about? Which part of the משנה
Mishnah: *mishnah* is this question relevant? אי נימא אשלא לשמה lishma ולשמה
*ee-eima ashelo lishma u'lishma*, if it's the part of the משנה mishna.
*mishnah* where the first thought or statement you made is the wrong
קרבן korban *korban*, the שלא לשמה shelo lishma *shelo lishma*, and then
you have the לשמה lishma *lishma*, בין בעבודה אחת בין בשתי עבודות
avodos בין רבי מאיר בין רבי יוסי יפסל דמיפסיל מקמייתא *bein b'avodah
achas bein bishtei avodos bein Rabbi Meir bein Rabbi Yose yifsil de-yifsilei
mi-kamaisa*. So there it doesn't matter, one עבודה avoda, *avodah*, two עבודות
*avodos*, רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose*, as soon as
you get the first words out of your mouth, I am doing
this for the sake of a שלמים shelamim. *shelamim*, it's already invalid,
right? Because everybody agrees that you're bound at least by the first
thing out of your mouth. So even רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* would
say that it's invalid when you said שלמים shelamim *shelamim* and then
פסח Pesach *pesach*, even in one sentence. Okay, there wouldn't be a
debate that that would be invalid. דהא de-ha רבי יוסי נמי אף
בגמר דבריו אדם נתפס *de-ha Rabbi Yose nami af bigmar devarav adam
nitpas*. According to רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose*, he doesn't say you just
look at the end, you say you even look at the end.
So everybody agrees you always go by the beginning. רבי מאיר *Rabbi
Meir* only goes by the beginning if it's a contradictory sentence, and
רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose* goes by the beginning and the end. So
if you started by saying the wrong thing, this is a שלמים
shelamim. *shelamim* and then you said and this is a פסח pesach
*pesach*, then everybody agrees it's invalid as soon as you got the
word שלמים shelamim. *shelamim* out of your mouth, you invalidated it.
Are we necessarily talking about speaking here?
Well, I'm saying saying because as I said before, there's a question
in the beginning of זבחים *Zvachim*, all these things that talk about
מחשבה *machshavah* that invalidates, you know, there's a רש"י *Rashi* and תוספות
*Tosfos* that talk about articulating it and saying it out loud. It
could be that even the thought alone invalidates. Then it raises interesting
questions about number one. One like about the evidence that it occurred,
but besides even proving whether it occurred or not, it raises an
interesting question about how much הלכה halacha. pays attention to things that
are not objective, not
measurable, they're not out there for other people to perceive, it's just
totally in your head. But there is a debate whether when we're
talking about the thought, whether it means articulated or not articulated thought.
I'm saying speaking because it makes it similar to these other statements,
it's easier to relate to that case.
What are the practical consequences of this? The כהן Cohen could go
through the whole process and then he's out and the owner doesn't
bring another one.
Well, yeah, the כהנים Kohanim would be responsible to inform the
owner.
If nobody knows, nobody knows.
Right. You're right. Look, Rivka, most of the next five פרקים prakim
is going to be theoretical
discussions. It's an opportunity for חז״ל Chazal to figure out the exact
הלכה halacha. parameters in the
reality of tens of thousands or hundreds of thousands of people bringing
the קורבן פסח, Korban Pesach, how much they could always deal with
this is a question, but the גמרא Gemara was not thinking practical.
The גמרא Gemara was dealing theoretical.
Okay, so you have to get out of the end of the
line when they came back with the second and they go back
to where they were standing.
Maybe what they did is they sort of like when you're coat
check, when you brought your פסח, pesach, they gave you one tag
and they put another tag on the קורבן, Korban, and then after
it got כשר, kosher, after it was done, they then gave you
back the other part of the tag.
But then if there are 20 people sharing this animal, right, what
do
they do?
They just add a plus? They have to go find themselves another
animal and do the whole thing again. I know. And that's an
interesting discussion in the גמרא Gemara in גיטין, Gittin, which is a
כהן Cohen that invalidates somebody's קורבן, Korban, does he have any civil
liability, right? Does he is he liable to compensate? And the basic
answer is no, but anyway, that issue is discussed.
Is stopping them from fulfilling the מצווה mitzvah of פסח pesach for
this.
Yeah, they wouldn't be over any כרת, Karet, they try whatever, they
bring a פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, but yeah, it's
unlikely you're going to accidentally think that this פסח pesach. is a
שלמים shelamim because
this is after the...
Right, the question is this might not be accidental, it might be
your intention, why you have these crazy thoughts in your head, I
don't know, but the more obvious scenario is accidental, but who knows
what you're thinking.
Did each קורבן Korban have its own individual ברכה? Bracha?
Otherwise, how would you know whether or not you'd said the wrong
thing?
Well, the wrong thing, oh, that's interesting. The wrong thing, I mean,
there is the גמרא Gemara just talks in one place after the
end of ברכות Berachot by the eating of קורבנות. Korbanot. I'm trying
to think if there's any discussion about the ברכות Berachot for bringing
of
קורבנות. Korbanot. But again, it's a bizarre scenario, the כהן Cohen just
says out loud, first of all, you don't do a ברכה Bracha
as you שחט, shacht, as you מקבל הדם, mekabel hadam, at each
one of the עבודות. הגמרא HaGemara never assumes that this is in
the context of some ברכה. Bracha. It's just some כהן Cohen makes
some declaration, I am doing this for whatever. It's hard to imagine
the scenario again if he's just thinking it then he got to
come and say, he's like a novice on the job, so he
says, he says actually I wasn't paying attention, what's, I was thinking
the wrong thing when I did this. So you could imagine a
case where he was thinking it. But again, going back to that
issue, is he actually saying it out loud? What would motivate him
to be making these types of declarations? So these are all good
practical questions, I understand, right? What would motivate, what would be the
scenario where he actually would say it? How would they deal with
it about letting the owners in, informing the owners? All of these
issues. הגמרא HaGemara is dealing with this purely as an intellectual question.
It's not addressing those issues. So let's see where הגמרא HaGemara goes
with this. Okay, אלא אי לשמו ושלא לשמו מאי? Ella, i lishmo
u'shelo lishmo mai?
What if you said the first the right thing, פסח, pesach. and
then you said the wrong thing, שלמים? shelamim So if it's one
sentence, then רבי מאיר should say no problem, you ignore the end.
So that's the question: was our משנה mishna in that case dealing
with one act or with two acts? Would רבי מאיר agree or
not? תא שמע, Ta shema, come in here. הפסח ששחטו שלא לשמו,
HaPesach she'shachto shelo lishmo,
let's look at our משנה. mishna The פסח pesach if you slaughtered
it
שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, וקיבל והלך וזרק שלא לשמו, ve'kibel ve'halach ve'zarak
shelo lishmo, היכי דמי? heichi dami? What's the case?
אי נימא כדקתני, Ei neima k'detani,
if it's like it sounds like you did all the four עבודות
שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, למה לי אדמחשב בכולהו? lama li ad'michashev bekulhu?
The ו vav here can't mean and. Why would you need to
do all of them wrong as long as you did one of
them wrong, you invalidated it, מאימת איפסל, me'eimat ipsal, from the very
first עבודה avoda you invalidated it. אלא לאו הכי קתני, Ella lav
hachi k'tani, the ו vav has to be read not as an
and but as an or. And here's how you read the משנה:
mishna הפסח ששחטו שלא לשמו, HaPesach she'shachto shelo lishmo,
if you slaughtered it שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, אי נמי, i nami,
or alternatively,
שחטו לשמו, shachto lishmo, maybe you did the שחיטה shechita. correctly, וקיבל
והלך וזרק שלא לשמו, ve'kibel ve'halach ve'zarak shelo lishmo,
but you did the other עבודות שלא לשמו shelo lishmo incorrectly. אי
נמי *ei nami*, or שחטו וקיבל והלך לשמו *shachto vekibel vehalach lishmo*,
you did everything correctly, except for the last one, וזרק שלא לשמו
shelo lishmo *vezarak shelo lishmo*, the last one was incorrect. Now, meaning
that is the פשט *pshat* of the משנה mishna *mishna*. It says
if you שחט *shacht* or caught the blood or walked the blood
or threw the blood שלא לשמו shelo lishmo *shelo lishmo*, the ו
*vav* means or, which means you did everything right and the last
one you did שלא לשמו shelo lishmo *shelo lishmo*, even that is
enough to invalidate. That a מחשבה *machshava* at any one of the
עבודות *avodot* is enough to invalidate. Now, in that scenario where it
was the last עבודה avoda, *avoda* שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo*, דהוה ליה
שתי עבודות *dehavei lei shtei avodot*, it's two עבודות *avodot*. The first
one is right and the second or the fourth one is the
wrong one. That's the first case of the משנה mishna *mishna*. So
the very first case of the משנה mishna. *mishna* where you did
the last one שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo* is a case of לשמו
ושלא לשמו *lishmo ushelo lishmo* in two separate עבודות *avodot*. So then
אימא סיפא seifa *eima seifa*, now let's look at the next case
of the משנה mishna *mishna*. לשמו ושלא לשמו *lishmo ushelo lishmo*, it
says the next case is the hybrid. So what the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is pointing out is a very good read of the משנה
mishna *mishna*. It says look, the very first case is different מחשבות
*machshavot* at different עבודות *avodot*. It talks about שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo*
at the end and לשמו *lishmo* at the beginning, right? That's the
simple read of the משנה *mishna*. So the end where it talks
about a hybrid
must be a hybrid during one עבודה avoda *avoda*, because we've already
related to the case of different מחשבות *machshavot* at different עבודות *avodot*.
So לשמו ושלא לשמו היכי דמי *lishmo ushelo lishmo heichi dami*, what's
the case at the end of the משנה *mishna* where it talks
about the hybrid? אילימא בשתי עבודות *eileima bishtei avodot*, if it means
one מחשבה *machshava* at one עבודה avoda *avoda* and one at another,
היינו רישא *hainu reisha*, that's exactly the first case. The first case
was you had the wrong מחשבה *machshava* at one of the עבודות
*avodot* and the right מחשבה *machshava* at the others. אלא ela לאו
*ela lav*, it must be when the end of the משנה *mishna*
deals with the hybrid case, בעבודה אחת *be'avoda achas*, we're talking about
two מחשבות *machshavot* during one עבודה avoda *avoda*. כרבי יוסי היא *ke-Rabbi
Yossi hi*, and you see our משנה *mishna* is going like רבי
יוסי *Rabbi Yossi*, דאמר אף בגמר דבריו אדם נתפס *de'amar af b'gmar
devarav adam nitpas*, you're held accountable, you're grabbed even by the end
of your words. And if you have a hybrid מחשבה *machshava* or
statement, you go by even the end of it and it invalidates.
Okay, pretty good read. The first part of the משנה *mishna* is
talking about separate עבודות *avodot*, the end of the משנה *mishna* seems
to be talking about a hybrid מחשבה *machshava* or statement during one
עבודה avoda, *avoda*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says לא *lo*, not
necessarily. לעולם בשתי עבודות *le'olam bishtei avodot*, I could say the whole
משנה *mishna* is talking about separate עבודות *avodot* where you have separate
מחשבות *machshavot*. So what's the difference between the first case and the
last case? רישא דקאי בשחיטה וקמחשב בשחיטה *reisha deka'i bishchita vekamachashev bishchita*,
there's two ways of having מחשבות *machshavot* at separate עבודות *avodot*. One
is מחשבה *machshava* during the act that you're doing. So the first
case is you had the wrong מחשבה *machshava* when you were שוחט
*shocheit*, you were thinking, "I'm שוחט *shocheit* it שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo*."
אי נמי *ei nami*, or when it's for example when you had
the wrong מחשבה *machshava* only at the end, קאי בזריקה וקמחשב בזריקה
*ka'i b'zrika vekamachashev b'zrika*, you're throwing the blood and you're thinking, "I'm
throwing the blood for the sake of a שלמים shelamim, *shlamim*." So
that's the case of the משנה *mishna* where it's separate עבודות *avodot*
and when you were doing the wrong one, you were the act
you were doing, you were having intent that this act is being
done שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo*. Fine. סיפא seifa, *seifa*, the end case
which spoke about a hybrid, here's how you get a hybrid
during one עבודה *avoda* but it's still about separate עבודות *avodot*. Let's
take a look. דקאי בשחיטה וקמחשב בזריקה *deka'i bishchita vekamachashev bizrika*, that
you're שוחט *shocheit* it but your bad מחשבה *machshava* is about what
you're going to do in the future. In that way, it's a
little bit like פיגול *pigul*, you're thinking about what you're going to
do in the future, not what you're doing right now. דאמר *de'amar*,
here's what you're saying: הריני שוחט את הפסח לשמו לזרוק דמו שלא
לשמו *hareini shocheit es haPesach lishmo lizrok damo shelo lishmo*. I'm שוחט
*shocheit* this קרבן פסח korban pesach. *korban Pesach* for the sake of
a קרבן פסח korban pesach *korban Pesach* with the intention that I'm
going to throw the blood for the sake of a שלמים shelamim
*shlamim*. So this guy has to be like a real להכעיס *lehach'is*
guy, I mean, what's he doing, right? Clearly he's not confused, he
knows that it's a פסח pesach *Pesach*, he's not doing it בטעות
*beta'us*, okay, and he's saying, "I'm שוחט *shocheit* it as a פסח
pesach *Pesach* to throw the blood as a שלמים shelamim *shlamim*." Okay,
so in terms of whether this is a practical scenario or not,
right, you can really wonder. So anyway, that's the hybrid case. Now,
meaning like this: if I had said a contradictory thing about the
same act, "I'm שוחט *shocheit* it לשמו *lishmo* for פסח pesach *Pesach*
and for a שלמים shelamim *shlamim*," then רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* would
say, "I'm just going to ignore the end of your sentence." Right,
make up your mind, either it's for פסח pesach *Pesach* or for
a שלמים shelamim. *shlamim*. But here it's not contradictory. I'm שוחט *shocheit*
it for a פסח pesach, *Pesach* and I'm שוחט *shocheit* it with
the intent to do the זריקה zrika. *zrika* for a שלמים shelamim
*shlamim*. So those are two, I mean, they're each statement by itself
stands. Okay, it's not like you're trying to do one act in
different ways. And therefore, that would be a case that even רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir* could agree with. דקא משמע לן *deka mashma lan*,
and this is teaching us דמחשבינן מעבודה לעבודה *demachshavinan me'avoda le'avoda*, that
you can have a מחשבה *machshava* from one עבודה *avoda* to another
even if you had it when you're doing שחיטה shechita *shchita*, you
were planning on doing the זריקה שלא לשמו *zrika shelo lishmo*, that
is enough to invalidate. והייא בעיא דרב פפא *vehai be'aya de-Rav Pappa*,
and that's why רב פפא *Rav Pappa* is asking whether the case
in the משנה *mishna* is a case of just everything on the
שחיטה shechita. *shchita*, or do we read the משנה *mishna* like רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir* and say the case of the hybrid is not
you have פסח pesach שלמים shelamim *Pesach shlamim* by שחיטה shechita. *shchita*,
but the hybrid case in the משנה *mishna*... is שחיטה shechita *shechitah*
for פסח pesach *Pesach* with the intention to do the זריקה *zrika*
for the שלמים shelamim, *shelamim*. Okay? So just repeat what we are
saying. Whether you have a לשמו *lishmo* or שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo*
that it invalidates. Everybody agrees that it invalidates at separate עבודות *avodot*,
because then the one עבודה *avodah* that you're doing שלא לשמו *shelo
lishmo* invalidates. Okay. The question is, what about if you have a
hybrid thought during one עבודה *avodah*? רבי מאיר *Rebbe Meir* would say
that's not a problem, I just look at the beginning of the
sentence. And רבי יוסי *Rebbe Yosi* would say I look at the
whole sentence. We acknowledge that the משנה *Mishnah* is talking about a
hybrid case, not just separate עבודות *avodot*, but we say no, that
could still be a case that רבי מאיר *Rebbe Meir* would invalidate
when it's not one sentence about the שחיטה shechita *shechitah* you're doing,
where it's actually two sentences during the שחיטה shechita, *shechitah*. One sentence
that the שחיטה shechita *shechitah* is לשמו *lishmo* and the other sentence
is that the זריקה *zrika* you're planning on doing שלא לשמו *shelo
lishmo*. That's the case that because it's not a hybrid, it's not
all about one and we won't truncate it, each one stands by
itself and it will invalidate. But if it's all about a hybrid
by שחיטה *shechitah*, there רבי מאיר *Rebbe Meir* would only look at
the beginning of the sentence, not at the end, and he would
salvage the קרבן korban *korban*. Okay. So that is still the question
about what would be, again, no question how the תנאים *Tannaim* would
hold, but a question about what is the case in the משנה
*Mishnah*.
So there's two different ways of understanding עבודה אחת *avodah achat* and
שתי עבודות *shtei avodot*.
Right. Well, שתי עבודות *shtei avodot* is always each act separate. When
you're doing the שחיטה *shechitah* you have a thought of שחיטה *shechitah*
שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo*, זריקה *zrika*, זריקה *zrika* שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo*.
The question is, our משנה *Mishnah* clearly has the scenario of עבודה
אחת *avodah achat*, which is a hybrid, which is the end of
the משנה *Mishnah*. But is it a pure עבודה אחת *avodah achat*?
I'm שוחט *shechting* it לשמו ושלא לשמו *lishmo u'shelo lishmo*? Or is
it an עבודה אחת *avodah achat* that relates to two עבודות *avodot*,
which is how רבי מאיר *Rebbe Meir* would read it. Okay. תא
שמע *tash ma*, come in here. Where are we? או שלא לשמו
ולשמו פסול pasul, *o shelo lishmo u'lishmo pasul*. Right? The end of
the משנה *Mishnah*, now we're at the very end of the משנה
*Mishnah*. It says for either שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo* and לשמו *lishmo*.
You started with the wrong thought for שלמים shelamim. *shelamim*. היכי דמי
*heichi dami*? What's the case? אילימא בשתי עבודות *i'lima beshtei avodot*?
If the שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo* was during one, during the שחיטה
*shechitah*, and the לשמו *lishmo* was during the זריקה *zrika*. השתא לשמו
ושלא לשמו אמרת פסול pasul. *hasha lishmo u'shelo lishmo amarta pasul*? When
you start correct, it's invalid if you ended with the wrong thought.
שלא לשמו ולשמו מיבעיא *shelo lishmo u'lishmo mibaya*? Of course if you
started by calling it a שלמים shelamim *shelamim*, you invalidate it right
at the get-go. So there would be no point of giving that
scenario in the משנה *Mishnah*. It's obvious that if it was talking
about two עבודות *avodot*. אלא בעבודה אחת *ella ba'avodah achat*? It must
be we're talking about a hybrid thought. You do one act and
you're thinking about it
being, this one שחיטה *shechitah* is שלא לשמו ולשמו *shelo lishmo u'lishmo*.
And there there's a big חידוש *chiddush*, since it's a hybrid thought,
maybe I would think that the end of the thought might dictate.
Okay. ומדסיפא בעבודה אחת U'mi'de'seifa b'avoda achas, *u'mi'de'seifa ba'avodah achat*, and since
the end is clearly talking about a hybrid thought, רישא נמי reisha
nami, בעבודה אחת *reisha nami ba'avodah achat*? The beginning also we're talking
about a hybrid thought for one עבודה *avodah*. מתקיף לה *metakef lo*?
No. לא לעולם בשתי עבודות *lo olam beshtei avodot*. The end we're
talking about two separate עבודות *avodot*. When you did the שחיטה *shechitah*
it was שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo*, when you did the זריקה *zrika*
it was לשמו *lishmo*. וכדינא דלא אצטריך ליה *v'kedina d'lo itztarich lei*,
and really there's no need to teach it. Of course, once you
did the שחיטה *shechitah* שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo*, end of story. ואיידי
דתנא לשמו ושלא לשמו *ve'aydi de'tana lishmo u'shelo lishmo*, but since we
gave the scenario of doing it לשמו *lishmo*, of starting with the
right thought, תנא נמי שלא לשמו ולשמו *tana nami shelo lishmo u'lishmo*.
We gave the scenario of starting with the right thought, but you're
right, the end is really redundant and obvious. Okay. So in the
end we're saying the משנה *Mishnah* is dealing with a, the simple
read is it's dealing with a hybrid case of עבודה אחת *avodah
achat*, but there's a way to read it that it's a type
of separate thoughts even during one act that even רבי מאיר *Rebbe
Meir* would agree to. תא שמע *tash ma*, come in here. So
now we're going to look at the next משנה *Mishnah*. This משנה
*Mishnah* is that you have intention, as I said, for a different
קרבן korban *korban*. The next משנה *Mishnah* is you have intention for
different owners. Okay? And how does that affect it? So let's take
a look. And I'll just tell you the basic difference is that
when you have intention for the wrong owners, if you just have
intention for a different group, you invalidate the פסח pesach, *Pesach* like
you had intention for a different קרבן korban *korban*. But if you
had intention for some of the right owners and some of the
wrong owners, that you guys over here were all part of this
קרבן פסח korban pesach *korban Pesach* and you guys were on a
different one, and as I'm שוחט *shechting* this קרבן פסח korban pesach
*korban Pesach*, I'm thinking I'm doing this for Charlie and for Seth.
So part of my thought was about the right owners and part
of it was about the wrong owners. That case is actually כשר
kosher *kasher*. So the hybrid thought by the wrong owners is valid,
whereas the hybrid thought of the wrong קרבן korban *korban* is invalid.
Okay? That's what the next משנה *Mishnah* teaches. So let's take a
look what we can learn from that about whether we're dealing with
one עבודה *avodah* or שתי עבודות *shtei avodot*. תא שמע *tash ma*,
come in here. לאוכליו ושלא לאוכליו כשר kasher *le'ochlav v'shelo le'ochlav kasher*.
If I slaughter it with the intent of both the right owners
and the wrong owners. Okay, it is כשר kasher, *kasher*. There's actually
a slight difference between לאוכליו *le'ochlav* and למנויו *le'minuyav*, but anyway we'll
worry about that tomorrow when we get to that משנה *Mishnah*. Okay.
היכי דמי *heichi dami*? What's the case? אילימא בשתי עבודות *i'lima beshtei
avodot*? If we're talking about two עבודות *avodot*, when I שוחט *shecht*
it I think about the owners and when I do the זריקה
*zrika*... I think about, I think about you know a group of
people that are the they're not the owners. Okay so it's not
a hybrid in one thought like I just gave the example I
just gave where I'm thinking about both together. No, at one act
I think about one group, and at the other act I think
about the other group. So וטעמא *v'tama* דחשב בזריקה *d'chashiv bizrika*. So
then the reason שלא לאוכליו shelo l'ochlav. *shelo l'ochlav* would be כשר
kasher. *kasher* as I'm throwing the blood and thinking about the wrong
owners is because it occurs during the throwing of the blood. דאין
מחשבת אוכלין בזריקה de'ein machsheves ochlin b'zrika. *d'ein machshevet ochlin bizrika*.
This is a very important point. The thought about the owners, about
the eaters as it were, is not relevant to the act of
the זריקת הדם *zrikat hadam*. Normally... what?
Did I skip a couple lines? Yeah. I'm sorry.
Okay I'm so eager I'm jumping to the end. Let's try that
again. תא שמע *ta shma* I'm sorry let's thanks go up to
the earlier. It's what we call השמטה ידי הדפוס *hashmata yedei hadfus*.
שחטו שלא לאוכליו shelo l'ochlav, ושלא למנויו *shachto shelo l'ochlav ushelo limnuyav*.
Thank you you shchted it either back to that that's to the
משנה *mishnah*. So they're either the people that שלא לאוכליו *shelo l'ochlav*
technically means not just the different group, it might be the right
group but let's say among the group are people that are unable
to eat it. They're sick, they're elderly, they can't eat the requisite
amount. They're טמא tamei. *tamei*, so they might be the right people
that are designated for it but not able to eat it. Or
שלא למנויו *shelo limnuyav* is the simpler case of people that are
part of a different group. ערלים וטמאים *arelim utme'im* or people, men
that are uncircumcised even for legitimate reasons let's say they're hemophiliacs or
people that are טמא *tamei*. Again that's similar to a לא לאוכליו
*lo l'ochlav* example. Although לא לאוכליו *lo l'ochlav* just might mean health-wise
can't eat it. פסול *pasul*. In all those cases if it's just
for that it's invalid. So הכא פשיטא בעבודה אחת *hacha pshita bavoda
achat*. So clearly that's a case because it's all about שחטו *shachto*.
It's all about the שחיטה *shchita*. So it's all talking about one
act. ומדסיפא בעבודה אחת *umid'seifa bavoda achat* since the סיפא *seifa* meaning
the next משנה *mishnah* is talking about one act. רישא נמי בעבודה
אחת *reisha nami bavoda achat*. Our משנה *mishnah* also is talking about
when it talks about a hybrid case is talking about one act.
So גמרא Gemara *gemara* says מידי איריא mi'dei irya, *midi irya*? Is
that a proof? הא כדאיתא והא כדאיתא Ha k'isaye ve'ha k'isaye, *ha
k'deita v'ha k'deita*. Each one is according to is going its own
way. סיפא בעבודה אחת Seifa b'avoda achas, *seifa bavoda achat* the case
of לאוכליו ולמנויו *l'ochlav ulimnuyav* is talking about is talking about one
act with the שחיטה *shchita*. רישא *reisha* and the first and our
משנה *mishnah* אי בעבודה אחת אי בשתי עבודות i b'avoda achas i
b'shtei avodos, *ee bavoda achat ee bishtei avodot* there's no way of
knowing whether this hybrid thought is at one act or two acts.
So you can't prove anything from that. That's very you know that's
a separate משנה *mishnah*. תא שמע *ta shma*. Now come in here
we're going to try again from that משנה *mishnah* but a slightly
stronger proof although the argument that every משנה *mishnah* is separate will
still be you know will still be given but at least this
next proof is a little bit
stronger. לאוכליו ושלא לאוכליו *l'ochlav ushelo l'ochlav*. The משנה *mishnah* goes on
to say if it's a hybrid thought of those that can eat
and can't eat. The group is made up of some people that
can eat and some can't and I'm thinking about all of them.
כשר kasher *kasher*. That's okay. היכי דמי *heichi dami*? What's the case?
אי נימא בשתי עבודות *ee neima bishtei avodot* if it means right
when you talk about two thoughts. If it means like we're trying
to argue maybe our משנה *mishnah* means two thoughts each one at
a different time. So when I do the שחיטה *shchita* I think
about those that can eat it. When I do the זריקה *zrika*
I intend it for the people that can't eat it. וטעמא *v'tama*
so when why would it not be invalid? דחשב בזריקה *d'chashiv bizrika*
because that thought about the wrong eaters is when I did the
זריקה *zrika*. דאין מחשבת אוכלין בזריקה *d'ein machshevet ochlin bizrika*. The thought
about the eaters is not relevant during the זריקה *zrika*. Now that
is a very important principle. What why? Because normally as
I
said all four עבודות *avodot* are relevant and any wrong thought can
invalidate it at any one of the עבודות *avodot*. And certainly you
know the one עבודה *avoda* that clearly would be the worst would
be the most central would be the זריקה *zrika*. That's the blood
that's what makes it a קרבן korban *korban*. By the קרבן פסח
korban pesach *korban pesach*, if you have a thought that it's a
שלמים shelamim, *shlamim* or an אשם *asham*, that's relevant for all the
עבודות *avodot* just like any other קרבן korban *korban*. But if you
have a thought related specifically to the mitzvah of eating the קרבן
פסח korban pesach. *korban pesach*, that is only a problematic thought during
the שחיטה *shchita*. Okay? Because the פסוק *pasuk* says איש לפי אכלו
תכסו על השה *ish lefi ochlo tachosu al haseh* that according to
those that are counted you should שחט *shacht* it. And specifically look
think about it. What's related most to eating something? Shchting it, right?
Turning it from an animal into meat. So this issue, again, it
points to the centrality of the eating of the פסח pesach, *pesach*
by the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach *korban pesach* which does not exist
by any other קרבן *korban*. So therefore the thought the emphasis of
the right people designated as the eaters that your wrong thought can
invalidate it at the moment of שחיטה *shchita*. שחיטה *shchita* is what
matters and nothing else. So therefore what the משנה *mishnah* says is
what the גמרא Gemara *gemara* is saying is, if we're talking about
separate acts, when you did the שחיטה *shchita* you were thinking about
the right people and when you were doing the זריקה *zrika* you
were thinking about the wrong people, then the reason it's valid is
not because hybrid things are valid by owner relating to owners, it's
because the second the second thought was irrelevant. It was not coming
during the שחיטה *shchita* period and the thought about the owners not
during the שחיטה *shchita* is I mean not the owners, the eaters.
not during the שחיטה is an irrelevant thought. So that's where the
גמרא Gemara says, אביי Abaye also says, the טעמא, ta'ama, then the
only reason it would be okay is not because it's a mixed
thought is okay. The reason it would be okay is דאין מחשבת
אוכלין בזריקה. Thinking about eaters is not relevant during the זריקה. הא
בעבודה אחת, Ha b'avoda achas,
so if it were during one עבודה, if it were a truly
hybrid thought during one act, כגון בשחיטה, kegon b'shechita, if you had
both thoughts during שחיטה, דמהני בי מחשבת אוכלין, de'mahani bei machsheves ochlin,
that's where the thought about eaters helps—helps doesn't mean helps, is relevant
and can affect the status of a קרבן—פסול, it would be invalid.
והא, Ve'ha, that would be implied by the משנה. The only reason
it's okay is because the bad thought was not during the שחיטה.
If it were during the שחיטה, even as a mixed thought, the
implication would be that it would be okay. וקיימא לן מקצת אוכלין
לא פסלה, Ve'kayma lan mixas ochlin lo pasla, we know our principle
is that a mixed thought, if only some of them are the
wrong eaters, it's not a problem. So basically what the משנה is
saying is the following. First tells you the גמרא—first gemara it tells
you this important principle that the only relevance of thinking about the
eaters is during שחיטה, which is shocking, again goes to the emphasis
of eating by the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach And the other thing
it says is we know, we have—you know, we have a tradition
that the idea is a whole difference between eaters versus שלא לשמה
shelo lishma is that a mixed thought is not a problem by
eaters. It's a problem by שלא לשמה, shelo lishma not by eaters.
So clearly the משנה that's talking about the eaters and having a
mixed thought and it being okay is talking about one עבודה because
any division makes it irrelevant because it's not during שחיטה. Only שחיטה—there's
only one עבודה that is relevant is the שחיטה. So there where
it's talking about a mixed thought it means a mixed thought during
שחיטה. So you see that משנה is saying that it's talking about
mixed thoughts during one עבודה and therefore for us too, we'll be
talking about mixed thoughts during one עבודה. אלא לאו בעבודה אחת, Ella
lav b'avoda achas, you see that משנה is talking about one עבודה.
ומדסיפא בעבודה אחת, so since the סיפא of the end where it's
mixed thoughts relating to the eaters is one עבודה—and again that's what
makes it more lenient that there a mixed thought is okay whereas
a mixed thought by the שלא לשמה shelo lishma, is invalid—but anyway
there clearly since it's only שחיטה we're talking about a mixed thought
during one עבודה, it's only שחיטה that's relevant. So רישא נמי, in
our case of the שלא לשמה shelo lishma where it's talking about
a mixed thought, בעבודה אחת, presumably is a mixed thought during one
עבודה and again you see that we're going according to רבי יוסי.
So the גמרא Gemara again says, מידי איריא, what is that a
proof? הא כדאיתא והא כדאיתא, each one is going according to its
own parameters. סיפא בעבודה אחת, the end, the סיפא, the next משנה
that's talking about about eaters is all during one עבודה, only שחיטה,
only שחיטה is relevant.
דרישא, De'reisha, our case, אי בעבודה אחת אי בשתי עבודות, there's no
way of knowing whether we're talking about a mixed thought during one
עבודה or during two עבודות. So and then the—so the גמרא does
not resolve it. Okay, clearly though the interesting, fascinating thing about this
is the גמרא never has a question about the הלכה. halacha It's
very clear to the גמרא that according to, you know, everybody would
agree if a thought at two separate עבודות invalidates—two separate thoughts at
two עבודות—that רבי מאיר would also invalidate if you were at one
עבודה and thinking about a different one, and that if it was
all a hybrid during one עבודה it would be a debate between
רבי מאיר and רבי יוסי. There's never a question about what's הלכה.
halacha The only question is how to read the משנה. Okay, and
there is certainly the simple sense is that the משנה reads like
רבי יוסי. The משנה reads if you have a thought, separate thoughts
at separate עבודות or a hybrid thought at one עבודה, either way
a mixed thought invalidates. By שלא לשמה shelo lishma a mixed thought
invalidates and by wrong owners—wrong eaters I should say—a mixed thought does
not invalidate. Okay so that's end of that discussion. Now the גמרא
goes on. איבעיא להו, Iba'ya lehu, this'll be a
little—a little easier I think. Okay, איבעיא להו, iba'ya lehu, they raise
the question. It's always—it's always dangerous to say that because and what
this is easier? Okay, פסח ששחטו בשאר ימות השנה לשמה ושלא לשמה
מהו. pesach she'shechato bish'ar yemos hashashana lishma u'shelo lishma mahu. You could
tell the גמרא is having fun. There's a הלכה which is the
following: if a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach normally is just like a
שלמים in the sense that the owners eat the meat, okay so
the קרבן that it's most like is the שלמים. Now, and you
could eat it in all of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So the הלכה interestingly
is is that if the קרבן פסח pesach is shechted not on
ערב פסח, erev pesach, it has the status of a שלמים, okay?
You actually it's כשר kasher. as a שלמים. Now there's two scenarios:
one is it's no longer—פסח pesach has passed, you were supposed to
have brought one פסח, pesach you lost it, you had to bring
another one and now פסח pesach has passed. In that case, even
with no particular thought, it automatically is designated as a שלמים because
you can't hold it over till next year because a קרבן פסח
pesach has to be a year old, within a year. So there,
even if you have a blank head, you know, you're not thinking
anything when you shecht it, its own status is redefined almost automatically
as a שלמים. But let's say... it's a month before פסח pesach
*Pesach*, it's פורים purim *Purim*, and you designated this nice sheep for
your קרבן פסח Pesach *Korban Pesach*, okay? And now you forgot about
it and you brought it to the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* and
you שחט *shecht*ed it. There, it's still it's its natural status is
a פסח Pesach *Pesach* because in a few weeks you can bring
it as a פסח Pesach, *Pesach*. But if you have an intentional
intention when you're bringing it, I'm bringing this as a שלמים *Shelamim*,
you can transform it into a שלמים *Shelamim*. Okay, that's a special
הלכה *halacha* that a פסח Pesach *Pesach* can be transformed when it's
not ערב פסח Pesach *Erev Pesach* into a שלמים *Shelamim*. If it's
after פסח Pesach *Pesach*, it automatically is that way. If it's before
פסח Pesach *Pesach*, only when you have the intention of bringing it
as such. Okay. Now the גמרא *Gemara* is going to have a
fun question. What if you brought the קרבן פסח Pesach *Korban Pesach*
on פורים purim *Purim* and you had a thought, I'm bringing this
as a פסח Pesach *Pesach* and as a שלמים *Shelamim*? You had
a mixed thought. But there, it's the שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo* that
makes this valid. If you had the thought of just a פסח
Pesach *Pesach*, it would be invalid. It would be a פסח Pesach
*Pesach* brought during the wrong time. But because you had a mixed
thought, so it's the שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo* that makes it valid
and the לשמו *lishmo* that makes it invalid. Which one would win
out? How does that hybrid similar to the hybrid of our משנה
*Mishnah*? Or wait, let's take the case. So it says like this.
איבעיא להו *Ibaia lehu*: פסח Pesach. ששחטו בשאר ימות השנה *Pesach
sheshachto bishear yemot hashana*. You shechted it earlier in the year, specifically
meaning let's say פורים purim *Purim*, לשמו ושלא לשמו *lishmo ushelo lishmo*,
for the right sake and for the sake of the פסח Pesach,
*Pesach*, which should make it invalid then it would be a פסח
Pesach, *Pesach* at the wrong time, but also שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo*
for the sake of a שלמים *Shelamim* which would make it valid.
Okay. מהו *Mahu*?
What's the הלכה *halacha*? מי אתי שלא לשמו *mi ati shelo lishmo*
does the שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo* thought, the שלמים *Shelamim*'s thought come,
ומפקי ליה מידי לשמו *umafkei leh miyedei lishmo* and take it out
of its status of a פסח Pesach *Pesach*, ומכשר ליה *umachshar leh*
and make it כשר kasher. *kasher*, או לא *o lo* or not?
Meaning in our משנה *Mishnah*, שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo* wins out when
it's a hybrid thought. Would שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo* win out as
well when the שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo* is making it valid? Or
no, maybe it's always the bad thought? In any hybrid thought, it's
always the bad one that creates the problems, whether it's the שלא
*shelo* or לשמו *lishmo* thought. If part of it is a bad
thought, that's a problem. So what's the סברא *sevara*? So כי אתא
רב דימי אמר *Ki ata Rav Dimi amar*, when רב דימי *Rav
Dimi* came from ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* he said, אמריתה לשמעתא קמיה
דרבי ירמיה *Amrita lishmata kammai deRabbi Yirmiyah*, I told over this discussion
to רבי ירמיה *Rabbi Yirmiyah*. הואיל ולשמו מכשירו בזמנו ושלא לשמו מכשירו
שלא בזמנו *Hoil ulishmo machshiro bizmano ushelo lishmo machshiro shelo bizmano*. And
here was my argument. Since לשמו *lishmo* makes it כשר kasher *kasher*
when it's ערב פסח *Erev Pesach* and שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo* makes
it כשר *kasher* all other times. מה לשמו המכשיר בזמנו אין מוציא
מידי שלא לשמו *Mah lishmo hamachshir bizmano ein motzi miyedei shelo lishmo*.
The good thought on ערב פסח *Erev Pesach*, לשמו *lishmo*, is not
strong enough to win out over the bad thought, over the שלא
לשמו *shelo lishmo*. So the same way there, meaning it's another way
of saying the presence of the bad thought invalidates, even though there's
a good thought there as well. אף שלא לשמו המכשיר שלא בזמנו
אין מוציאו מידי לשמו ופסול *Af shelo lishmo hamachshir shelo bizmano ein
motzio miyedei lishmo upassul*. Similarly on the rest of the year, the
שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo* which is the good thought which will make
it כשר *kasher* now that it's not ערב פסח *Erev Pesach*, the
presence of that good thought is not strong enough to take it
out מידי לשמו *miyedei lishmo* from the presence of the bad thought,
and it's invalid. Which is totally the reasonable assumption I think we
would have said. If the point is a hybrid thought is no
good, then it doesn't matter which is the good part of that
thought and which is the bad part of that thought. The presence
of a bad thought is going to be a problem. That's what
I said. That's so that's what I said to רבי ירמיה *Rabbi
Yirmiyah*. ואמר לי *Veamar li*, and רבי ירמיה *Rabbi Yirmiyah* said back
to me, לא *lo*, not necessarily. I can make the argument that
here it's better. Why? אם אמרת בשלא לשמו *Im amarta bishelo lishmo*,
why does שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo* win out in a hybrid thought
and invalidate in our משנה *Mishnah*? שכן נוהג בכל הזבחים *Sheken noheig
bechol hazvachim*. That is a פסול *psul*, an invalidity that applies to
all קרבנות *korbanot*. שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo* makes all קרבנות *korbanot*, you
know, invalid or at least problematic that it doesn't count for the
owners. So שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo* is a universal פסול *psul*. So
therefore in our case of a hybrid thought in the משנה *Mishnah*,
it trumps. תאמר בלשמו *Tomar bilishmo*, in your case, when it's when
it's before when it's פורים purim *Purim*, right? Which is the פסול
*psul*? The bad thought is the לשמו *lishmo* thought. If you think
about it that way, right? So לשמו *lishmo* is never a bad
a an invalidating thought except in this one case. Okay, this is
the only case in the world where לשמו *lishmo* is an invalidating
thought, when it's פורים purim, *Purim* and you're bringing your קרבן פסח
*Korban Pesach*. So there, שכן אינו נוהג בכל הזבחים *sheken eino noheig
bechol hazvachim*. In all other קרבנות *korbanot*, לשמו *lishmo* is never an
invalidating thought, אלא בפסח בלבד *ela bePesach bilvad*, except by the פסח
*Pesach*. So he basically says the לשמו *lishmo* thought is not so
powerful to invalidate. שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo* is like a real you
know, you know, stain on the קרבן *korban*. That's an invalidity that
always applies. And if that's present even in a hybrid thought, it's
a problem. But in our case, when it's פורים *Purim* and לשמו
*lishmo* is the bad thought, that's not such an invalidating thought. So
therefore it doesn't have the power to win out and to invalidate
in the case of a hybrid thought. Okay, so we don't know.
It's an interesting question. מאי הוי עלה *Mai havi alah*? What was
the conclusion of this discussion? אמר רבא rava *Amar Rava*, so רבא
rava *Rava* said: פסח ששחטו בשאר ימות השנה *Pesach sheshachto bishear yemot
hashana*... פסח ששחטו בשאר ימות השנה לשמה lishma, ושלא לשמה lishma כשר.
So רבא rava says I actually think it's כשר and the לשמה
does not win out. Now, maybe for the reason we said before
it's not such a strong invalidity, but he's actually going to prove
it by an analogy. What is his analogy?
דהסתמא לשמה קאי. da-stama lishma ka'i. He says think about פורים and
forget that you had a mixed thought. Here it was, it was
פורים and you were shechting it לשם שלמים. That would make it
כשר, right? But רבא rava says but on its own, meaning the
קרבן taken by itself, is designated for a פסח. It's standing for
a פסח. So it's as if there's the already purpose of a
פסח there and nevertheless, right, when you do it שלא לשמה, shelo
lishma you make it כשר. So your שלא לשמה shelo lishma in
a normal
scenario, you shecht your פסח on פורים for the sake of a
שלמים. Your thought of a שלמים
wins out against the לשמה that the קרבן itself represents. So he
says therefore if you said them both, that's not making it any
worse. Okay, the קרבן already represents a פסח and your thought of
a שלמים wins out. So even if you say פסח and שלמים,
your thought of a שלמים will win out. That's רבא's rava, analogy.
Does the קרבן פסח doesn't have to be designated within the first
ten days?
No, I mean minimally you're supposed to set a, you know, קרבן
aside a few days before to check it for a מום mum
and so on, but you can sanctify it a long time before.
Sanctify it earlier?
Right. And if it makes you happier we could say we're talking
ten days before פסח or four days before פסח, but I just
wanted to give פורים as a more graphic example when we're talking.
Okay, the גמרא says like this,
so where was רבא saying it? דהסתמא לשמה קאי. da-stama lishma ka'i.
In a normal scenario when שלא לשמה shelo lishma makes it כשר
on פורים, the פסח itself represents קרבן פסח. That's what it's going
to be used for in a month. ואפילו הכי כי שחט ליה
שלא לשמה כשר ve-afilu hachi ki shachat leh shelo lishma kasher and
nevertheless your thought of שלמים wins out and makes it כשר. אלמא
אתי שלא לשמה ומפקי ליה מידי לשמה alma atei shelo lishma u-mafkei
leh midei lishma so שלא לשמה shelo lishma, trumps the לשמה even
to validate it, even though the so in that case the שלא
לשמה—it's not the invalid thought wins out, the שלא לשמה wins out
and in that case and validates it. So since that's true by
a normal case, כי שחט נמי לשמה ושלא לשמה, ki shachat nami
lishma u-shelo lishma, even if you say the words לשמה, אתי שלא
לשמה ומפקי ליה מידי לשמה, atei shelo lishma u-mafkei leh midei lishma,
your thought of a שלמים will come
and take it out of its designation of a פסח and turn
it into a שלמים. So that's his argument that that case should
be good based on the analogy of a case where you don't
say anything, that still the presence of the idea of לשמה is
automatically there. אמר ליה רב אדא בר אהבה לרבא, amar leh rav
adda bar ahava le-rava, so רב אדא בר אהבה rav adda bar
ahava didn't buy this. He said to רבא, דילמא שאני היכא דאמר
מהיכא דלא אמר. dilma shani heicha de-amar me-heicha d-lo amar. He said
a very reasonable spot—no, I'm sorry,
maybe it's different when you don't say something as opposed to when
you do say something. When you do say something, you're compromising your
own sentence. Meaning when you say שלמים and it represents a פסח,
fine, it's your statement against what the קרבן represents. But when you're
saying שלמים and פסח, your own statement is compromised, so it weakens
the statement. So maybe it is different when you say something. דהא
and here's the
example, דהא לאוכליו ושלא לאוכליו כשר. de-ha le-ochlav u-shelo le-ochlav kasher. Take
the case we were talking about before. If you had an intention
for a that the people you were when you were shechting it,
there would be eaten by this group, some of who can eat
it and some of who cannot eat it. So that mixed thought
is כשר. וכל היכא דשחיט ליה שלא לאוכליו לחודיה פסול. ve-chol heicha
de-shachit leh shelo le-ochlav lechudei pasul. So that we know, a mixed
thought is כשר when it comes to the eaters. But how about
if you had just a thought of the wrong eaters, that would
be invalid. וכל היכא דשחיט ליה שלא לאוכליו לחודיה פסול. ve-chol heicha
de-shachit leh shelo le-ochlav lechudei pasul. If you shechted it with the
thought of the wrong eaters only, it's פסול. ואמאי? ve-amai? Why? That
should be like a hybrid thought. Because the פסח on its own
is designated for the right
eaters. דהסתמא לאוכליו קאי. da-stama le-ochlav ka'i. Because you know so why
don't you just combine your thought of the wrong eaters with the
natural designation of the פסח for the right eaters and make it
valid and call it a hybrid thought? אלא—obviously you don't do that.
You don't combine what the פסח represents with what you're saying. אלא
שאני היכא דאמר מהיכא דלא אמר. ela shani heicha de-amar me-heicha d-lo
amar. It matters whether you said a hybrid thought or whether it
was created you know or whether you didn't say anything and the
פסח just represented it. So when you said a hybrid thought it's
okay by the eaters, when the when you only said one thought
the פסח can't make it better. הכא נמי, hacha nami, here too,
שאני היכא דאמר מהיכא דלא אמר. shani heicha de-amar me-heicha d-lo amar.
It's different saying and not saying. When you just say שלא לשמה,
that wins out. When you yourself say a hybrid thought, maybe it
does not. So you can't use what the פסח represents to be
say that as you know that's sort of supplying the other half
of the sentence. It's not true. It's very different when your own
thoughts are mixed as opposed to they are only represented only one
thing. אמר ליה. amar leh. Rava did not like the comparison. מי
דאיריא? Mi deirya? What, that's a
comparison? בשלמא התם, Bishlama hasam, there the פסח does not provide, as
it were, the right idea of the right
eaters. קמיה דלא עקריה בשחיטה—sorry, Kamei delo akreih bishchita excuse me, התם
hasam meaning over there. And over there
by the פסח on Purim, קמיה דלא עקריה בשחיטה, kamei delo akreih
bishchita, as long as you do not change its status by shechting
it for the sake of a שלמים, סתמיה דפסחא ושמו קאי. stamei
dePascha ushmo kaei. There is no other identity to this פסח, meaning
this is sanctified as a קרבן פסח even though it's Purim. And
the only way its status can change is if you shechted it
as a שלמים. There's nothing else you can do to change its
status. אלא הכא, Ela hacha, but by the eaters case where you
said why doesn't the פסח represent the right eaters, סתמיה לאוכליו קאי?
stamei l'ochlav kaei? Would you say a
פסח is only related to specific
eaters? דילמא מימשכי הני ואתו אחריני? Dilma mimshichi hanei v'asu achrinei? Who
are the eaters of a פסח can constantly change. You're allowed to,
the group can change before it's slaughtered. Some people can withdraw from
the group and other people can join into the group. Maybe some
will withdraw their hands and other people will join, דתנן, detnan, we
taught in a Mishna: נמנין ומושכין ידיהם ממנו עד שישחט, Nimnin umoshchin
yedeihem mimenu ad sheyishachet, that you can add on to the group
and remove your hands from the group, meaning withdraw from the group,
until it is slaughtered. So what Rava is saying is the following.
He's saying you prove that you do not use the natural status
of the קרבן פסח to create a hybrid reality from the case
of שלא לאוכליו. That if you are thinking שלא לאוכליו, you don't
say ah the פסח represents the right eaters, it's a hybrid, it's
kosher. So you see you don't use the פסח to create a
hybrid. But that's only because the פסח doesn't fully represent its natural,
the people that are currently designated. That's like a moving target. Who
are the eaters of a פסח can change over time, so it's
not like it's full identity. So to have a mixed up there
you need to say the owners and you need to explicitly articulate
the right owners. The פסח doesn't fully represent the owners to create
a mixed reality because that's a changing status. But in the case
of shechting it on Purim, this the only identity of this animal
is a פסח. There's no way its status is going to naturally
change. And therefore Rava says since in that case when you say
שלמים it wins out over the unchanged status of this as a
פסח, over the more, you know, the fully sort of owned status
of this as a פסח, when you say שלמים, so therefore even
if you say both it's still going to win out. Your statement
of שלא לשמו trumps. If it trumps the קרבן פסח where this
is its full identity, it'll trump even when you say a hybrid
statement. So that's Rava's position. Of course even with that being said
you can understand the response. No, you know, if when it's you
against the קרבן you could win out. But when you yourself are
of a compromise, you know, type of a position, you say both,
maybe it weakens your own statement and the, you know, and that's
the other side of it. So this is the גמרא having fun
of taking a hybrid where not the שלא לשמו invalidates in our
Mishna, but by the פסח on Purim where the שלא לשמו would
validate, would it be the same or not. Okay, that we will
end.
The
thing about this is the...
it's such a difference, the character of the דף daf is so
different, you know?
The thing I wanted to do was the necessity to change from...
that has to change even, even in night if someone accidentally becomes
טמא.
Ah yeah, but then that's true but there's one thing that you're
part of the group and not able to eat it and there's
another thing where you officially, officially withdraw from the group.